<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
    <title>ls-lrt.com - MachineLearning</title>
    <subtitle>Blog Site of Samir Parhi</subtitle>
    <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://ls-lrt.com/tags/machinelearning/atom.xml"/>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://ls-lrt.com"/>
    <generator uri="https://www.getzola.org/">Zola</generator>
    <updated>2024-09-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://ls-lrt.com/tags/machinelearning/atom.xml</id>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>Physics in Product Metaphor: Navigating Momentum Through Pivot</title>
        <published>2024-09-18T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2024-09-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        
        <author>
          <name>
            
              Samir Ranjan Parhi
            
          </name>
        </author>
        
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://ls-lrt.com/mastering-the-art-of-pivot/"/>
        <id>https://ls-lrt.com/mastering-the-art-of-pivot/</id>
        
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://ls-lrt.com/mastering-the-art-of-pivot/">&lt;h2 id=&quot;generalization&quot;&gt;♺ Generalization:&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pivot! Simply put, it’s change—a sustainable and universal reality. Every entity on this planet, whether it’s an individual, a business, or anything else, inevitably goes through pivots.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We tend to appreciate products that build momentum, and the same goes for businesses. Both continuously aim to gain momentum, which, in physics, is defined as the product of an object’s mass and velocity (momentum = mass × velocity).&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the context of a business or product:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mass:&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; could be seen as the complexity, features, or baggage of a product&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Velocity:&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; could represent the rate of progress or adaptability&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s correlate Physics and Business Metaphor:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;rocket-momentum-and-fabric-interaction&quot;&gt;🚀 Momentum and Fabric Interaction:&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If a product is too complex (heavy), it can become less adaptable, causing the business to struggle (tear the fabric). However, if it has a high rate of innovation or agility (&lt;code&gt;velocity&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;), it compensates for the heaviness, allowing the product to move forward despite the complexity. Let’s plot it :&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;&#x2F;img&#x2F;blog&#x2F;pivot-intro.svg&quot;&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;X-Axis:&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;  Business relevance over time, The idea is that a product must continuously stay relevant in time by adapting.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Y-Axis:&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; Rate of Change in Technology A higher Y-value indicates a company adopting more cutting-edge or future technologies.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Z-Axis:&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; (Rate of Product Innovation &#x2F; Pivot): How frequently or drastically a product is innovating or pivoting.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;case&quot;&gt;Case ① :&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A product overloaded with unnecessary features (high Z-value) can only succeed if it evolves and adapts very rapidly (high Y-value) to meet market demands. Without this agility, the excess weight of unused features slows it down, limiting its momentum on the time (X) axis.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;case-1&quot;&gt;Case ② :&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A “light” product—small, focused, and purposeful—can pivot easily along the X-axis. Launching with a minimum viable product (MVP) allows for quicker adjustments and faster adaptation (moderate Y-value) without overburdening the product with unnecessary features (low Z-value).&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;case-shift-on-y-and-z-axes&quot;&gt;Case ③ : Shift on Y and Z Axes:&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moving toward Y (cutting-edge technology) or Z (frequent pivots&#x2F;innovations) in isolation can hinder progress. A product that is too futuristic (high Y-value) or innovates too frequently (high Z-value) may lose momentum because it loses focus or overextends resources on experimentation without bringing value.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;koko-classifying-a-product&quot;&gt;🈁 Classifying a Product :&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;rock-heavy&quot;&gt;🪨 Heavy :&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Too many features but not enough users:&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; The product is packed with features, but they aren’t reaching or being used by customers&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;High upfront spending without enough research:&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; A lot of money is spent early on without properly understanding the market.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Building out of fear instead of demand:&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; The product is created just to follow trends (FOMO) rather than addressing real customer needs.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Outdated technology:&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; The product isn’t keeping up with new technology or improvements in its tech stack.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;train2-light&quot;&gt;🚆 Light :&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Purpose-driven design:&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; The product is built with a clear purpose, solving specific customer problems.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fewer features, more users:&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; Focusing on fewer, more essential features that users actually need and want.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Low upfront costs:&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; Managing costs carefully in the early stages, keeping spending low.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fast feedback and quick adjustments:&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; Getting feedback early on and adapting quickly, even before the product is fully launched, making it easier to pivot.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;brain-final-thought&quot;&gt;🧠 Final Thought&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In physics, space-time is a fabric that can bend, and similarly, in business, the passage of time and external forces (technology, market trends) can “bend” the business environment. A heavy product can warp this fabric, slowing progress. A light, nimble product moves more easily across it.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hope you like it. ❀&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
        
    </entry>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>Battle of Programming Language: Statically Typed Vs Dynamically Typed ?</title>
        <published>2024-09-17T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2024-09-17T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        
        <author>
          <name>
            
              Samir Ranjan Parhi
            
          </name>
        </author>
        
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://ls-lrt.com/statically-typed-and-dynamically-typed-programing-language-intro/"/>
        <id>https://ls-lrt.com/statically-typed-and-dynamically-typed-programing-language-intro/</id>
        
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://ls-lrt.com/statically-typed-and-dynamically-typed-programing-language-intro/">&lt;h2 id=&quot;wood-the-tree-analogy-defining-tall-in-programming&quot;&gt;🪵 The Tree Analogy: Defining “Tall” in Programming&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Take a real-world object like a tree 🌴. When you describe it with an adjective, you define it based on that descriptor. The interesting thing about adjectives is that they’re not always tied to specific, measurable details. For instance, if you say the tree is tall, everyone understands the tree is tall, but how tall is subjective and varies from person to person, depending on their personal scale. For example, to me, a tree taller than 8 feet is considered tall, but for you, that might not be the case. You might think a tree over 10 feet is tall. Still, we both agree it’s tall.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This concept of subjectivity in adjectives can be closely linked to understanding statically typed programming languages and general-purpose programming languages (which are often dynamically typed).&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;fast-forward-statically-typed-languages&quot;&gt;⏩ Statically Typed Languages&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Languages like &lt;code&gt;C++&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;Rust&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; demand you explicitly define types upfront. This precision leads to optimizations that make them a solid choice for high-performance machine learning systems.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;zap-performance-benefits&quot;&gt;⚡ Performance Benefits:&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Compile-Time Optimization:&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; Just as a precise adjective removes ambiguity and potential miscommunication, statically typed languages catch many errors during compilation.Since types are known before execution, compilers generate highly efficient machine code, reducing CPU and memory overhead.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Efficient Memory Usage:&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; Explicit type definitions mean better memory management, allowing these languages to make the most out of system resources. It gives precision and prevents ambiguity.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Parallelization:&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; Allow you to fine-tune control over CPU cores and even leverage GPUs and TPUs for heavy machine learning tasks.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;warning-challenges&quot;&gt;⚠️ Challenges:&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Inflexibility:&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; Requiring everything to be explicitly typed or defined can slow down development, especially for prototyping or situations where the types aren’t clear at the start.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Verbosity:&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; It adds extra code and complexity for things that might not need it in simple scenarios.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Slower Iteration:&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; Refactoring and iterating quickly might be harder when you need to make sure all types are aligned correctly.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;snake-dynamically-typed-languages&quot;&gt;🐍 Dynamically Typed Languages&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Flexibility and Adaptability:&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; Dynamically typed languages (like &lt;code&gt;Python&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;JavaScript&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;Ruby&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;) are more like using the adjective “tall” without a strict definition. They are flexible and allow you to work without having to define everything explicitly. This suits exploratory or rapidly changing contexts.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ease of Use:&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; You can be more casual in your descriptions (or code) without worrying about errors until they actually show up during runtime. This can lead to faster development in certain scenarios.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;construction-challenges&quot;&gt;🚧 Challenges:&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Potential for Miscommunication:&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; Just as the word “tall” might mean different things to different people, in a dynamically typed language, the same function or variable can change in unexpected ways, causing confusion or errors.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Slower Execution:&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; Runtime type checking and interpretation add overhead, making dynamically typed languages slower in terms of raw CPU performance.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Higher Memory Overhead:&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; Without predefined types, dynamically typed languages often consume more memory, which may limit performance when handling large datasets.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Less Optimization:&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; Without knowing the exact types, compilers&#x2F;interpreters can’t optimize as well as they could in statically typed languages.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;brain-case-studies&quot;&gt;🧠 Case Studies&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;1-statically-typed-languages&quot;&gt;1. Statically Typed Languages:&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mission-Critical Applications:&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; Where errors need to be minimized at all costs (e.g., banking systems, aerospace software). The precision of static typing ensures that fewer unexpected behaviors occur.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Large, Complex Systems:&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; Where maintaining clear structures and interfaces is essential for scalability. Static typing helps maintain clarity and prevents issues during refactoring.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Performance-Optimized Code:&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; Static typing allows for better optimization during compile time, leading to more efficient runtime performance.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;2-dynamically-typed-languages&quot;&gt;2. Dynamically Typed Languages&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Prototyping and Rapid Development:&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; Where speed of development is key, and the exact structure or types may not be fully understood in the early stages. Flexibility allows quick iterations.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Small or Medium-Sized Applications:&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; Where the complexity is lower, and the risk of runtime errors is acceptable or manageable.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Data Science, Web Development, Scripting:&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; Fields where flexibility and rapid changes are needed more than strict type enforcement. For example, many web frameworks in &lt;code&gt;Python&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;JavaScript&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; thrive on the ease of use provided by dynamic typing.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;page-with-curl-summary&quot;&gt;📃 Summary&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Statically Typed Languages:&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; Offer precision and safety but are less flexible and can slow down development in exploratory phases. They are suited for large-scale, performance-sensitive, or mission-critical systems.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dynamically Typed Languages:&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; Offer flexibility and speed but at the cost of potential runtime errors and less optimization. They are suited for prototyping, rapid development, and smaller-scale projects.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;thought-balloon-open-thought&quot;&gt;💭 Open Thought&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Can &lt;code&gt;Rust&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; Be the Next Machine learning language ? or We train the Machine Using &lt;code&gt;Python&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;Julia&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;, then use them using &lt;code&gt;Rust&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; ?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
        
    </entry>
</feed>
